Guide to the Eugene Clyde Brooks Papers, 1774-1971 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Eugene Clyde Brooks papers 1774-1971 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Brooks, Eugene Clyde
4.1 Linear Feet 3,105 Items
Professor of Education at Trinity College, Durham NC.
Collection chiefly is composed of letters, educational reports, numerous writings and addresses, and various professional papers, all relating to tobacco relief, education, and agriculture in North Carolina. Specific topics cover the Department of Education of what was then known as Trinity College in Durham, N.C.; the history of North Carolina, from an unpublished draft; and the matter of education for rural populations in N.C. and elsewhere. Materials include a microfilm of Brooks' papers held by the Department of Archives and History in Raleigh, N.C.; telegrams; extensive manuscripts for unpublished works, lecture notes, an address by Supt. Benjamin Lee Smith of Greensboro Public Schools. Other items in the collection include a scrapbook; cards from Brooks to his wife from abroad; original poems written by Brooks; photographs; memorabilia; an itinerary of his trip with other agricultural experts to Europe; a contract in manuscript drawn up in 1774 between citizens of Mecklenburg Co. and John Patterson, a school teacher, who was engaged to teach there; a printed document concerning Judge Walter Clark; and other miscellaneous items. There is also a printed copy of the diary of Dr. J. F. Shaffner, Sr. and blueprints of the N.C. State Fairgrounds.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Eugene Clyde Brooks Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1954-1972.
Collection Overview
Collection chiefly is composed of letters, educational reports, numerous writings and addresses, and various professional papers, all relating to tobacco relief, education, and agriculture in North Carolina. Specific topics cover the Department of Education of what was then known as Trinity College in Durham, N.C.; the history of North Carolina, from an unpublished draft; and the matter of education for rural populations in N.C. and elsewhere. Materials include a microfilm of Brooks' papers held by the Department of Archives and History in Raleigh, N.C.; telegrams; extensive manuscripts for unpublished works, lecture notes, and an address by Supt. Benjamin Lee Smith of Greensboro Public Schools. Other items in the collection include a scrapbook; cards from Brooks to his wife from abroad; original poems written by Brooks; photographs; memorabilia; an itinerary of his trip with other agricultural experts to Europe; a contract in manuscript drawn up in 1774 between citizens of Mecklenburg Co. and John Patterson, a school teacher, who was engaged to teach there; a printed document concerning Judge Walter Clark; and other miscellaneous items. There is also a printed copy of the diary of Dr. J. F. Shaffner, Sr. and blueprints of the N.C. State Fairgrounds.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Brooks, Eugene C. (Eugene Clyde), 1871-1947
Clark, Walter
Patterson, John, fl. 1774
Shaffner, J. F.
Smith, Benjamin Lee
Trinity College (Durham, N.C.)--Dept. of Education
Duke University. Dept. of Education -- History
Duke University. Dept. of Education -- Faculty
Agriculture -- North Carolina
Education, Higher -- North Carolina
Education, Rural -- North Carolina
Educators -- North Carolina -- Correspondence
American poetry -- North Carolina
Public schools -- North Carolina -- Mecklenburg County -- History -- 18th century
Public spaces -- Design
Public spaces -- North Carolina
Rural conditions -- Study and teaching
Tobacco -- North Carolina
Mecklenburg County (N.C.)--History
North Carolina -- Higher education
North Carolina -- History
Raleigh (N.C.)--History
Diaries
Blueline prints
Memorabilia
Microforms
Photographs
Scrapbooks
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1894-1971, (4 boxes)
  - 1894-1925 July (Box 9)
  - 1925 Aug.-1927 June (Box 10)
  - 1927 July-1933 Mar. (Box 11)
  - 1933 Apr.-1971 (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1928-1933 and undated, (10 boxes)
  - Scrapbook (Box 2)
  - Clippings (Box 4)
  - Miscellany
  - N.C. Park Commission records (Box 5-7)
  - Land grant college material (Box 7)
  - Elementary education material
  - Equalization Fund material
  - County Government Advisory Commission material (Box 8)
  - Papers, 1928-1933 (Box 12)
  - Printed material (Box 14)
  - Volumes (Box 15)
  - Educational reports (Box 16)
  - Microfilm from State Archives
- Writings Series, (9 boxes)
  - Writings and Addresses (Box 1-3)
  - Original Poems (Box 7)
  - North Carolina: A History of Government, Agriculture, Industry and Education, unpublished (Box 17-19)
  - The Education of a North Carolinian, unpublished
  - History of Educational Practice, unpublished (Box 20)
  - History of Educational Practice, unpublished (Box 21)